Guide to the Philippe David papers and photograph album M2058
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Philippe David papers and photograph album
1920-1946
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
David, Philippe, 1894-
M2058
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Biographical / Historical
Philippe David was a colonial administrator in French Syria and Lebanon from 1920-1946. Born in Dijon (Cote d'Or) on July 7, 1894, he wed Marthe Marie Antoinette Chevoit in Beirut on September 22, 1922. In 1923 his Paris University dissertation, "Un Gouvernement Arabe à Damas: Le Congrès Syrien," was published. He served over 6 years in Aleppo and 20 years in Beirut. He held several different roles over the years, including Chef du Bureau du Contieux, Rapporteur du Conseil d'Enquete (1922), acting Secretaire General de la Delegation de France au Levant (1945), and Conseiller de la Délégation Générale, Administrateur en Chef des Colonies, Directeur du Personnel et du Materiel (1946).
Scope and Contents
This archive contains Philippe David's files during most of the period he served in Syria and Lebanon, and covers the early period leading up to the French Mandate from the League of Nations through the war period up until his repatriation in 1946. Includes personal papers, correspondence, newspapers, magazines, photographs, documents related to David's career, documents realted to government and politics, press articles, photographs, and other material.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Syria -- History -- French occupation, 1918-1946; Syria -- Politics and government; David, Philippe, 1894-; History Revealed
- Papiers personnels (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondance personnelle (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Newspapers and magazines (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Memoires du General Catroux in Le Figaro, 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Beyrouth - etudes legislatives (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Reports (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Novels from L. Deangeli (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Syrie - Aleppo, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Rappels historiques par Phillipe David (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1921-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Beyrouth, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Policy in Syria, September 12, 1939-February 22, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Bulletin d' Information de la Delegation d'Alep, July 7, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Services speciaux du Levant, 1941 and Delegation d'Alep (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Elections in Lebanon, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Confidential documents, 1941-1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Philippe David's career, 1932-1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Maps from newspapers, 1939-1942 [?] (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Memories of General Weygand (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Memories of Marechal Petain, published in newspaper (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Memories of the General Guderian, published in newspapers (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Memories of Marechal Petain, published in newspapers (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Newspaper articles (French) (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Newspapers in Arabic language (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Other copies of the novels found in box 1 folder 7 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Photographs of Philippe David (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Décoration de “Commandeur de l’étoile de la Grande Comore” May, 26th 1949 for Mr. David (Flat-box 3, Folder 1)
- Photograph album: Deir-ez-zor, Abou-Kemal, [Syria] 1933-1934 (Flat-box 3)